Hello everyone, TDSW Youtube Channel!
From now on, I'm going to write a new article titled "GLSL for TouchDesigner
I'd like to talk about GLSL.
please help me
First of all, what is GLSL?
So that's what I'm saying.
GLSL stands for OpenGL Shading Language, and
In this case, OpenGL is called the Open Graphics Library.
It's a library that handles 3D graphics
Finally, as the word Language indicates, it is a programming language
You may hear the word "shader" a lot.
A blog that says in one word what Shader is all about.
I found it and I'm going to take a look at it.
This is Shibuya Hotogisu Tsushin's
I'll try to sum up in my own words what a "shader" is
So here's what we're going to look at
A program for displaying 3D objects on a display
And here it is defined as
I've made a little diagram of what this is all about.
See here
There's a 3D object, and then something happens.
It means that a 3D object will eventually appear on this display
You know, like a graphics pipeline in the 3DCG world.
We call it a rendering pipeline or something like that.
That's the case with OpenGL.
It means that the Shader is running in this
There is a thing called the Shader stage in the Shader.
So this is how some processes work.
There are a few places in there where programmers can actually write code
Since 3D objects are made up of triangular faces
So there are an awful lot of vertices.
The first thing to do is to use the
It's called the Vertex Shader.
Another one called Fragment Shader.
There is a Shader that handles the pixels
These two are basically the main shaders you'll be writing
And more.
It is called Geometry Shader.
Shader, which allows you to increase or decrease the amount of primitive, and
It's called the Compute Shader.
This is something that runs outside of this graphics pipeline, though.
It's a Shader for general purpose calculations and stuff like that.
This one doesn't work on a Mac, but here's what I've got
This is what we call a Shader.
GLSL uses the
I think you could call it a programming language
It could be 3DCG lighting, or image processing, or effects.
It's used in filters and such.
Some people make sounds with it.
When you can write this GLSL in TouchDesigner
I know it's a little bit different from the description.
It can also be used in other software and frameworks
For example, openFrameworks, Processing, and
You can also use it for WebGL and so on.
In other 3D software
For example, even if it's something that doesn't write code
I think it's very useful because you can apply the idea
It's more like a knowledge of matrices and linear algebra and stuff like that.
Although I think it's easy to understand GLSL better
I'm talking to you now, because I used to be a humanities guy myself, and
As someone who started studying this kind of thing after studying programming, I'm not a fan of
The mindset of this series is to just try it for now.
I'd like to move on.
So, in TouchDesigner, we're going to use
It's about how GLSL is used.
Mr. Higa, who has been speaking at TDSW many times as a lecturer
There's a good summary on the lecture page and I'd like to see this
This one.
Higa's first day of lectures in 2019
This is the first article on getting started.
I'll have them go downstairs.
There's a table like this and how the so-called TouchDesigner is organized.
I think it's a really good chart that's easy to understand.
This GLSL is basically the same as the one I mentioned earlier.
So it's often used for 3DCG.
So this TOP, this so-called 2D or material
SOP in 3D, where the vertex processing takes place
This is where GLSL will be used.
Why are we here?
If you ask me if I use GLSL.
So you're trying to use what's called a GPU to do the processing.
Here's a video showing the difference between the CPU and GPU.
I'd like to take a look at it.
This video, but it's done by a company that makes GPUs.
Of course, I think it's GPU superiority.
If it was a CPU, it would be like this, piece by piece
It's a process that takes a lot of time and a video that looks like it's going to take this long.
When you do this kind of work on the GPU
It's like being able to do parallel processing all at once like this and draw a picture.
Here's a comparison video like this one.
It's not that GPUs are better at everything, of course, but
The simpler these tasks are, the better.
It's like it's faster to do things in parallel on the GPU.
It's used a lot in the world of 3D and stuff like that.
As Higa-san wrote, there is a CPU and GPU.
GPUs are faster, so it's better to go with them as much as possible
So I'd like to proceed with that.
When actually writing a GLSL in TouchDesigner, you can use
GLSL TOP and GLSL Multi TOP and
It's called the GLSL MAT.
In the beginning, I used just GLSL TOP for a while.
I'm going to do a lot of things that you can do with Fragment Shader
It's about processing 2D pixels, so this can be an effect or
I can create animations and so on.
Amazing people are in this Fragment Shader.
We also create 3D worlds.
I'd like to do a little bit of that actually.
First, you have to get rid of all this.
Place the GLSL
It's like this.
This is what it looks like when I put it in place.
When you look at this place, sir.
It says Vertex Shader and Pixel Shader.
I heard it's called Fragment Shader in OpenGL.
It's called a Pixel Shader here.
In my research, I found that Fragment Shader and Pixel Shader
I'm sure there's a description for both of them, but you can assume they're the same thing.
In this GLSL TOP, the Pixel Shader, in addition to this
You can write a Compute Shader
In the meantime, I might do it later.
I'd like to use the Pixel Shader this time.
I'd like to take a look at the code inside.
Basically, all the processing is done in the main function
This fragColor is called
fragments of all colors
This one here is called vec4 color.
With the name of the variable named color of type vec4
This has four floats inside it
I could write it this way.
That's the equivalent of four 1.0s.
It's kind of like saying it's written in shortened form.
This is something that is RGBA.
R, G, B, A and
For example, if you set this place to 0 and 0.
This would be an R.
It's like this.
I know the last one here is an A, but I can change this one.
The A's are a bit different at this point.
This last one, this one called TDOutputSwizzle
This is, you know, originally a Windows and Mac
Because of the different way the textured alpha information is stored.
This function absorbs these OS differences
So I'm sure there are probably a lot of people using Macs.
Be sure to include this when you output the color at the end!
Anybody with a TD on their head is basically
I'm almost certain that it is a TouchDesigner specific function, so you can use
Remember.
This editor in TouchDesigner is good, though.
I use an external editor.
It's just that it's easier to write that way.
As you go through the settings, you can press Edit.
It will open in an external editor
I'm using VSCode.
Whatever.
If it's free, like Sublimte Text.
I'm sure that's part of it.
The way this is set up.
Edit - Preference
Alt P is fine.
From here we go to a place called DATs.
Here is where you can specify the path to the text editor.
I'm specifying the VSCode path here
If you specify this, the
When you press Edit here, you'll see that
It will open in an external text editor
The changes you make here are immediately reflected here
That's how it works.
This one is called glsl1_info, and it's a
So you can see the status here.
For example, if there is something wrong with this code.
It will give you an error here.
You can see what's wrong with it.
For example, if it was now, lines 10 and 11 would be
He'll tell you there's something wrong with you.
I find it useful for debugging.
This is an introduction, so that's all I'm going to do.
I'll be writing some actual code next time.
In addition to the Youtube tutorials on TDSW
We offer live streaming workshops about two weekends a month.
If these tutorials have piqued your interest in TDSW
Please come and visit us at our live streaming workshops!
Also, TDSW uses Patreon
Currently, we have a plan to support the creation of Youtube and an unlimited number of videos for workshops.
There are three plans: Workshop video and unlimited live streaming plan
This is more affordable than attending a stand-alone workshop
I hope you will consider it.
Please check out the link in the summary section!
Well, thank you for watching.
Please subscribe to the channel if you'd like.